This is poo,
هذا بوو (روث)،
and what I want to do today is share my passion
و الذي اود أن افعله اليوم هو أن اشاركم شغفي
for poo with you,
بـ الروث،
which might be quite difficult,
و الذي قد يكون صعب قليلاً ،
but I think what you might find more fascinating
و لكن اظن أن ما قد تجدونه آخاذاً اكثر
is the way these small animals deal with poo.
هو الطريقة التى تتعامل بها هذه الحيوانات الصغيرة مع الروث .
So this animal here has got a brain
هذه الحيوانات لديها عقل
about the size of a grain of rice, and yet it can do things
فى حجم حبة الأزر ، و على الرغم من ذلك يمكنها أن تقوم باشياء
that you and I couldn't possibly entertain the idea of doing.
انا و انت لا يمكننا على الأرجح أن نستمتع بفكرة القيام بها .
And basically it's all evolved to handle its food source,
و بشكل اساسي ، كل هذا تطور ليمكنها من التعامل مع مصدر غذائها ،
which is dung.
و الذي هو "الروث" .
So the question is, where do we start this story?
لذا فإن السؤال هو ، من أين نبدأ هذه الحكاية ؟
And it seems appropriate to start at the end,
و يبدو من المناسب أن نبدا من النهاية ،
because this is a waste product that comes out
لأن الروث هو مُنتَج مُهدر يخرج
of other animals, but it still contains nutrients
من حيوانات أخري ، و يحتوي على مواداً غذائية
and there are sufficient nutrients in there
و فيه ما يكفي من العناصر الغذائية
for dung beetles basically to make a living,
لتعيش عليه خنافس الروث بشكل اساسي ،
and so dung beetles eat dung, and their larvae
و بما أن "خنافس الروث" تتغذي على الروث و كذلك يرقاتها
are also dung-feeders.
ايضاَ تتغذي على الروث .
They are grown completely in a ball of dung.
فإنهم يعيشون بشكل كامل فى بحيرات من الروث .
Within South Africa, we've got about 800 species of dung beetles,
فى جنوب أفريقيا ، لدينا حوالي 800 نوع من "خنافس الروث" ،
in Africa we've got 2,000 species of dung beetles,
و فى أفريقيا عامةً لدينا 2000 نوع و فصيلة من "خنافس الروث" ،
and in the world we have about 6,000 species of dung beetles.
و فى العالم لدينا نحو 6000 نوع من "خنافس الروث" .
So, according to dung beetles, dung is pretty good.
لذلك ، من وجهة نظر الخنافس ، فإن الروث جيد جداً .
Unless you're prepared to get dung under your fingernails
إذا لم تكن مستعدا لأن يصبح الروث تحت أظافرك
and root through the dung itself, you'll never see
وأن تحفر في الروث ، فإنك لن ترى
90 percent of the dung beetle species,
90 بالمئة من فصائل خنافس الروث.
because they go directly into the dung,
لأنهم يتجهون مباشرة إلى داخل الروث،
straight down below it, and then they shuttle back and forth
بشكل مباشر إلى الأسفل، ومن ثم يسافرون ذاهبا وايابا.
between the dung at the soil surface
بين الروث وسطح التربة
and a nest they make underground.
والعش الذي يصنعونه تحت الأرض.
So the question is, how do they deal with this material?
لذلك السؤال هو كيف يتعاملون مع هذه المادة؟
And most dung beetles actually wrap it into a package of some sort.
إن أغلب خنافس الروث تلفها كرزمة من نوع ما.
Ten percent of the species actually make a ball,
عشرة بالمئة من الفصائل تنتج كرة،
and this ball they roll away from the dung source,
والتي يدحرجوناها بعيدا عن مصدر الروث،
usually bury it at a remote place away from the dung source,
ويطمرونها عادة بعيدا عن مصدر الروث،
and they have a very particular behavior
ولديهم نمط معين من التصرف
by which they are able to roll their balls.
والتي يمكنهم من دحرجة هذه الكرات.
So this is a very proud owner of a beautiful dung ball.
ماتشاهدونه الآن هو مالك فخور لكرة روث جميلة.
You can see it's a male
إنه ذكر
because he's got a little hair on the back of his legs there,
لأن لديه القليل من الشعر على الجزء الخلفي من أرجله،
and he's clearly very pleased about what he's sitting on there.
وهو بكل وضوح سعيد بما يجلس عليه هناك.
And then he's about to become a victim
وبعد ذلك هو على وشك بأن يكون ضحية
of a vicious smash-and-grab. (Laughter)
لسحق وإنتزاع شرير (ضحك).
And this is a clear indication
وهذا مؤشر واضح
that this is a valuable resource.
بأن هذا المصدر ذو قيمة عالية.
And so valuable resources have to be looked after
ولأن المصادر القيمة يجب الحفاظ عليها
and guarded in a particular way, and we think
وحمايتها بطريقة محددة، نحن نعتقد
the reason they roll the balls away is because of this,
بأن السبب الذي يجعلها تدحرج الكرات بعيدا هو ذلك،
because of the competition that is involved
لأن المنافسة هنا
in getting hold of that dung.
هي عبارة عن الإحتفاظ بالروث.
So this dung pat was actually -- well, it was a dung pat
لذلك هذا الروث حقيقة -- بالأصح، كان روثا
15 minutes before this photograph was taken,
قبل 15 دقيقة من التقاط الصورة،
and we think it's the intense competition
ونحن نعتقد أن المنافسة الشديدة
that makes the beetles so well-adapted
والتي تجعل من الخنافس متكيفة جدا
to rolling balls of dung.
لدحرجة كرات الروث.
So what you've got to imagine here is this animal here
عليك تخيل هذا الحيوان هنا
moving across the African veld.
يتحرك عبر مروج عشبية افريقية.
Its head is down. It's walking backwards.
رأسها للأسفل. وتمشي بالعكس.
It's the most bizarre way to actually transport your food in any particular direction,
إنها واحدة من أكثر الطرق غرابة لنقل الطعام لأي اتجاه،
and at the same time it's got to deal with the heat.
وفي نفس الوقت يجب لهذه الطريقة أن تتعامل مع الحرارة.
This is Africa. It's hot.
إنها إفريقيا. إنها حارة.
So what I want to share with you now
ما أود مشاركتكم به الآن
are some of the experiments that myself and my colleagues
هو بعض التجارب التي درسناها أنا وزملائي
have used to investigate how dung beetles
عن كيفية تعامل خنافس الروث
deal with these problems.
مع هذه المشاكل.
So watch this beetle,
شاهد هذا الخنفس،
and there's two things that I would like you to be aware of.
وهناك شيئين أريد منك أن تكون متنبها لهما.
The first is how it deals with this obstacle
الأول كيف تتعامل مع العوائق
that we've put in its way. See, look, it does a little dance,
والتي وضعناها في طريقها. انظر، شاهد، انها ترقص قليلا،
and then it carries on in exactly the same direction
ومن ثم تتابع إلى نفس الإتجاه تماما
that it took in the first place.
والذي أخذته في المرة الأولى.
A little dance, and then heads off in a particular direction.
رقصة صغيرة، ومن ثم يتجه إلى اتجاه محدد.
So clearly this animal knows where it's going
واضح جدا بأن هذه الحيونات تعرف إلى أين تذهب
and it knows where it wants to go,
وهي تعرف إلى اين تريد الذهاب،
and that's a very, very important thing,
وهذا شيء في غاية الأهمية
because if you think about it, you're at the dung pile,
تخيل معي، أنت واقف بجانب كومة الروث،
you've got this great big pie that you want to get away from everybody else,
ولديك كومة الشطائر الرائعة والتي تريد أن تأخذها بعيدا من الأشخاص الآخرين،
and the quickest way to do it is in a straight line.
فإن أسرع طريقة لفعل ذلك هو فعله بخط مستقيم.
So we gave them some more tasks to deal with,
لذلك أعطيناهم مجموعة أخرى من المهام ليتعاملو معها،
and what we did here is we turned the world
والذي فعلناه هنا بأننا أدرنا الآرض
under their feet. And watch its response.
من تحت أرجلهم. شاهد استجابتها لذلك.
So this animal has actually had the whole world
هذا الحيوان أدير العالم من تحت أرجله
turned under its feet. It's turned by 90 degrees.
أدير بزاوية 90 درجة.
But it doesn't flinch. It knows exactly where it wants to go,
لكنه لم يحجم. هو يعرف تماما إلى أين يريد أن يذهب،
and it heads off in that particular direction.
وهو يتجه مباشرة بهذا الإتجاه المحدد.
So our next question then was,
سؤالنا الثاني هو،
how are they doing this?
كيف يفعلون ذلك؟
What are they doing? And there was a cue that was available to us.
ماذا يفعلون؟ وهل هناك تلميح متوفر لدينا.
It was that every now and then they'd climb on top of the ball
بين الحين والآخر يقومون بتسلق الكرة
and they'd take a look at the world around them.
ويشاهدون العالم من حولهم.
And what do you think they could be looking at
وإلى ماذا تتصور أنهم ينظرون
as they climb on top of the ball?
عندما يتسلقون الكرة إلى أعلى؟
What are the obvious cues that this animal could use
ماهي الدلائل البديهية التي يمكن لهذه الحيوانات استخدامها
to direct its movement? And the most obvious one
لتوجه حركتها؟ وأكثرها بداهة
is to look at the sky, and so we thought,
هو النظر إلى السماء، لذلك فكرنا،
now what could they be looking at in the sky?
إلى ماذا يمكنهم النظر في السماء؟
And the obvious thing to look at is the sun.
والشيء البديهي هو النظر إلى الشمس.
So a classic experiment here,
لذلك قمنا بتجربة كلاسيكية،
in that what we did was we moved the sun.
بتحريك الشمس.
What we're going to do now is shade the sun with a board
ما سنقوم بفعله الآن هو عمل ظل للشمس بلوح
and then move the sun with a mirror
ومن ثم نحرك الشمس بمرآة
to a completely different position.
إلى مكان مختلف تماما.
And look at what the beetle does.
وونظر إلى ماتقوم الخنافس بفعله.
It does a little double dance,
إنها ترقص بشكل مضاعف،
and then it heads back in exactly the same direction
ومن ثم تتجه بالضبط إلى الإتجاه نفسه
it went in the first place.
والتي ذهبت إلى في المرة الأولى.
What happens now? So clearly they're looking at the sun.
ماذا يحدث الآن؟ بكل وضوح إنهم يبحثون عن الشمس.
The sun is a very important cue in the sky for them.
الشمس هي دليل مهم لهم في السماء.
The thing is the sun is not always available to you,
لكن الشمس ليست دائما متوفرة لك،
because at sunset it disappears below the horizon.
لأنها تختفي تحت الأفق عند المغيب.
What is happening in the sky here
ماذا يحدث للسماء هنا
is that there's a great big pattern of polarized light in the sky
أنه هناك نمط كبير من الضوء المستقطب في السماء
that you and I can't see. It's the way our eyes are built.
والذي لا أستطيع أنا أو أنت رؤيته. إنها الطريقة التي بنيت بها أعيننا.
But the sun is at the horizon over here
لكن الشمس في الأفق هنا
and we know that when the sun is at the horizon,
ونحن نعلم أنه عندما تكون الشمس في الأفق،
say it's over on this side,
افترض أنها فوق هذا الجزء،
there is a north-south, a huge pathway across the sky
هناك شمالا وجنوبا، كمية كبيرة من الدروب عبر السماء
of polarized light that we can't see
من الضوء المستقطب لا نستطيع رؤيتها
that the beetles can see.
والتي تستطيع الخنافس رؤيتها.
So how do we test that? Well, that's easy.
كيف نفحص ذلك؟ هذا سهل.
What we do is we get a great big polarization filter,
ما نقوم به هو وضع مرشح للاستقطاب،
pop the beetle underneath it, and the filter is at right angles
ندخل الخنفس تحته، ويكون بذلك الفلتر في الزاوية المناسبة
to the polarization pattern of the sky.
لنمط الإستقطاب في السماء.
The beetle comes out from underneath the filter
يخرج الخنفس من تحت الفلتر
and it does a right-hand turn,
ومن ثم تستدير إلى اليمين،
because it comes back under the sky
لأنها تعود تحت السماء
that it was originally orientated to
والتي توجهت لها أساسا
and then reorientates itself back
ومن ثم تقوم باعادة توجيه نفسها مرة أخرى
to the direction it was originally going in.
إلى الإتجاه الذي كانت ذاهبة له بالأساس.
So obviously beetles can see polarized light.
إذن وبشكل بديهي تستطيع الخنافس رؤية الضوء المستقطب.
Okay, so what we've got so far is,
حسنا، ما استنتجناه حتى الآن هو،
what are beetles doing? They're rolling balls.
ماذا تفعل الخنافس؟ إنها تدحرج الكرات.
How are they doing it? Well, they're rolling them in a straight line.
كيف يفعلون ذلك؟ حسنا، إنهم يدحرجونها بخط مستقيم.
How are they maintaining it in a particular straight line?
كيف يحافظون على الخط المستقيم؟
Well, they're looking at celestial cues in the sky,
بالبحث عن دلائل عليا في السماء،
some of which you and I can't see.
بعضها لا نستطيع أنت وأنا رؤيتها.
But how do they pick up those celestial cues?
لكن كيف يختارون هذه الدلائل السماوية؟
That was what was of interest to us next.
هذا هو ما اهتممنا به بعد ذلك.
And it was this particular little behavior, the dance,
إن ذلك التصرف الظريف المحدد،أقصد الرقص،
that we thought was important, because look,
الذي توقعناه مهما، لأنه انظر،
it takes a pause every now and then,
انها تقف بين فترة وأخرى،
and then heads off in the direction that it wants to go in.
ومن ثم تتجه إلى الإتجاه الذي تريد الذهاب إليه.
So what are they doing when they do this dance?
ماذا تراهم يفعلون عندما يقومون بهذه الرقاصات؟
How far can we push them before they will reorientate themselves?
إلى أي حد نستطيع أن ندفعهم قبل أن يعيدوا توجيه أنفسهم؟
And in this experiment here, what we did was we forced them
وفي هذه التجربة هنا، ما فعلناه هو اننا أجبرناهم
into a channel, and you can see he wasn't
إلى الدخول في قناة، وكما ترى لم يجبر على الدخول في
particularly forced into this particular channel,
هذه القناة المحددة،
and we gradually displaced the beetle by 180 degrees
ومن ثم وبشكل متدرج قمنا بازاحة الخنفس بزاوية 180
until this individual ends up going in exactly the opposite direction
حتى انتهى الأمر بهذا الفرد أن يذهب بالإتجاه المعاكس تماما
that it wanted to go in, in the first place.
للاتجاه الذي أراد الذهاب له بالأساس.
And let's see what his reaction is
دعونا نرى ماهو رد فعله
as he's headed through 90 degrees here,
عندما يتجه بزاوية 90 هنا،
and now he's going to -- when he ends up down here,
وهنا هو يسير -- وعندما ينتهي به المطاف هنا،
he's going to be 180 degrees in the wrong direction.
سيكون في الاتجاه الخطأ بزاوية قدرها 180 درجة.
And see what his response is.
وانظر ماهي ردة فعله.
He does a little dance, he turns around,
انها يمارس رقصة صغيرة، يستدير،
and heads back in this. He knows exactly where he's going.
ومن ثم يتجه مرة أخرى إلى هنا. انه يعرف تماما إلى أين يذهب.
He knows exactly what the problem is,
إنه يعرف بالضبط ماهي المشكلة،
and he knows exactly how to deal with it,
ويعرف بالضبط كيف يتعامل معها،
and the dance is this transition behavior
والرقص هو سلوك التحول
that allows them to reorientate themselves.
الذي يسمح لهم باعادة توجيه أنفسهم.
So that's the dance, but after spending many years
إذن هذه الرقصة، لكن بعد قضاء سنوات عديدة
sitting in the African bush watching dung beetles on nice hot days,
جالسا في أدغال أفريقيا أشاهد خنافس الروث في أيام جميلة حارة،
we noticed that there was another behavior
لاحظنا بأن هناك سلوكا آخر
associated with the dance behavior.
مرتبط بسلوك الرقص.
Every now and then, when they climb on top of the ball,
بين الحين والآخر، عندما يتسلقون إلى أعلى الكرة،
they wipe their face.
يمسحون أرجلهم.
And you see him do it again.
وانظر اليه يفعلها مرارا.
Now we thought, now what could be going on here?
هذا يجعلنا نفكر، ماذا يحصل هنا؟
Clearly the ground is very hot, and when the ground is hot,
بكل وضوح الأرض في غاية الحرارة، وعندما تكون الأرض حارة،
they dance more often, and when they do this particular dance,
يرقصون بشكل أكبر، وعندما يقومون بهذه الرقصة المحددة،
they wipe the bottom of their face.
يمسحون أسفل أقدامهم.
And we thought that it could be a thermoregulatory behavior.
ونحن نعتقد أن ذلك من الممكن أن يكون سلوكا لتنظيم الحرارة.
We thought that maybe what they're doing is trying to
اعتقدنا أنه ربما مايفعلونه هو محاولة
get off the hot soil and also spitting onto their face
الفرار من التربة الحارة بالإضافة للبصق على وجوههم
to cool their head down.
لتبريد رؤوسهم.
So what we did was design a couple of arenas.
من أجل معرفة الحقيقة قمنا بتصميم مجموعة من الميادين.
one was hot, one was cold.
أحدهم حار، والآخر بارد.
We shaded this one. We left that one hot.
ظللنا هذا. وتركنا هذا حارا.
And then what we did was we filmed them with a thermal camera.
بعد ذلك قمنا بتصوريرهم بكميرا حرارية.
So what you're looking at here is a heat image
ما تنظر إليه هنا هو صورة حرارية
of the system, and what you can see here emerging
للنظام، وما تستطيع رؤيته هنا يتصاعد من
from the poo is a cool dung ball.
الروث هو كرة روث باردة.
So the truth is, if you look at the temperature over here,
الحقيقة، أنه إذا نظرت إلى درجة الحرارة هنا،
dung is cool. (Laughter)
ستجد بأن الروث بارد (كوول) . (ضحك)
So all we're interested in here is comparing the temperature
ما يهمنا هنا هو مقارنة حرارة
of the beetle against the background.
الخنفس مقارنة بالأرض.
So the background here is around about 50 degrees centigrade.
درجة حرارة الأرض هي حوالي 50 درجة مئوية.
The beetle itself and the ball are probably around about
درجة حرارة الخنفس والكرة هي حوالي
30 to 35 degrees centigrade,
30 إلى 35 درجة مئوية،
so this is a great big ball of ice cream
لذلك هذه كرة كبيرة من البوظة
that this beetle is now transporting across the hot veld.
والتي تقوم هذه الخنفسة بنقلها عبر الواحة الحارة.
It isn't climbing. It isn't dancing, because
هي لا تتسلق. هي لا ترقص، لأن
its body temperature is actually relatively low.
درجة حرارة جسمها منخفضة نسبيا.
It's about the same as yours and mine.
هي تقريبا مشابه لدرجة حرارة جسمك وجسمي.
And what's of interest here is that little brain is quite cool.
وماهو مثير للاهتمام بأن هذا الدماغ الصغير ممتاز (كوول).
But if we contrast now what happens in a hot environment,
لكن إذا فعلنا العكس الأن ماذا سيحدث في البيئة الحارة،
look at the temperature of the soil.
انظر إلى درجة حرارة التربة.
It's up around 55 to 60 degrees centigrade.
انها حوالي 55 إلى 60 درجة مئوية.
Watch how often the beetle dances.
انظر كم مرة ترقص الخنفسة.
And look at its front legs. They're roaringly hot.
وانظر إلى أرجلها الأمامية. انها حارة جدا.
So the ball leaves a little thermal shadow,
تترك الكرة ظلال حراريا صغيرا،
and the beetle climbs on top of the ball
وتتسلق الخنفس إلى أعلى الكرة
and wipes its face, and all the time it's trying to cool itself down,
وتمسح وجهها، وفي كل المرات تحاول أن تبرد نفسها،
we think, and avoid the hot sand that it's walking across.
هذا هو اعتقادنا، وتتجنب حرارة التراب الذي تمشي عليه.
And what we did then was put little boots on these legs,
ومافعلناه بعد ذلك هو وضح أخذية صغيرة على هذه الأرجل،
because this was a way to test if the legs
لأن هذه طريقة لفحص ما إذا كانت الأرجل
were involved in sensing the temperature of the soil.
مسؤولة عن تحسس حرارة التربة.
And if you look over here, with boots they climb onto the ball
وإذا نظرت هنا، مع الأحذية تتسلق الخنافس الكرة بشكل أقل
far less often when they had no boots on.
مقارنة بعدم وجود أحذية.
So we described these as cool boots.
لذلك نصف هذه باحذية التبريد.
It was a dental compound that we used to make these boots.
استخدمنا مركب له علاقة بالأسنان لعمل هذه الأحذية.
And we also cooled down the dung ball, so we were able
وقمنا كذلك بتبريد كرات الروث، لذلك كنا قادرين
to put the ball in the fridge, gave them a nice cool dung ball,
على وضع الكرة في الثلاجة، واعطائهم كرة جميلة وباردة من الروث،
and they climbed onto that ball far less often
وكانت النتيجة أن الخنافس تسلقت الكرة بشكل أقل
than when they had a hot ball.
من عندما كانت الكرة حارة.
So this is called stilting. It's a thermal behavior
هذا يسمى التدعيم. هو سلوك حراري
that you and I do if we cross the beach,
نقوم به أنت وأنا عندما عندما نعبر الشاطيء،
we jump onto a towel, somebody has this towel --
نقفز على منشفة ، أحدهم لديه هذه المنشفة --
"Sorry, I've jumped onto your towel." --
"آسف، لقد قفزت على منشفتك." --
and then you scuttle across onto somebody else's towel,
وبعدها تركض عبر منشفة شخص آخر،
and that way you don't burn your feet.
وبهذه الطريقة تتجنب حرق قدميك.
And that's exactly what the beetles are doing here.
وهذا هو بالضبط ماتقوم الخنافس بفعله هنا.
However, there's one more story I'd like to share with you,
على كل حال، هناك قصة أخرى أريد أن أشارككم بها،
and that's this particular species.
عن هذه الفصائل المحددة.
It's from a genus called Pachysoma.
هي من جنس اسمه Pachysoma .
There are 13 species in the genus, and they have
هنالك 13 فصيل من هذا الجنس، ولديهم
a particular behavior that I think you will find interesting.
سلوك محدد والذي أعتقد بأنك ستراه ممتعا.
This is a dung beetle. Watch what he's doing.
هذا خنفس الروث. انظر ماذا يفعل.
Can you spot the difference?
هل تستطيع أن تلاحظ الفرق؟
They don't normally go this slowly. It's in slow motion.
إنها لا تسير بهذا البطء بشكل طبيعي. إنها بالعرض البطيء.
but it's walking forwards,
لكنها تمشي للأمام،
and it's actually taking a pellet of dry dung with it.
وهي في الحقيقة تأخذ حبة صغيرة من الروث المجفف معها.
This is a different species in the same genus
هذا صنف آخر من الجنس نفسه
but exactly the same foraging behavior.
لكن لديه نفس سلوك انتزاع المؤن.
There's one more interesting aspect of this
هناك شيء آخر ممتع لسلوك خنفس الروث هذا
dung beetle's behavior that we found quite fascinating,
والذي نجده مذهلا إلى حد ما،
and that's that it forages and provisions a nest.
وهو أنها تزود الطعام والمؤن للعش.
So watch this individual here, and what he's trying to do
شاهد هذا الفرد هنا، وما يحاول فعله
is set up a nest.
هنا هو اقامة عش.
And he doesn't like this first position,
لم يعجبه المكان الأول،
but he comes up with a second position,
لذلك جاء بمكان آخر،
and about 50 minutes later, that nest is finished,
وبعد 50 دقيقة، انتهى بناء العش،
and he heads off to forage and provision
وذهب لجلب المؤن والبحث عن الطعام
at a pile of dry dung pellets.
في كومة من القطع الصغيرة من الروث الجاف.
And what I want you to notice is the outward path
وما أريدك أن تلاحظه هو المسار الخارجي
compared to the homeward path, and compare the two.
مقارنة بمسار الإتجاه نحو المنزل، ومقارنة الإثنين.
And by and large, you'll see that the homeward path
سترى بأن مسارالإتجاه نحو المنزل
is far more direct than the outward path.
هو مباشر أكثر من المسار الخارجي.
On the outward path, he's always on the lookout
في المسار الخارجي، هو دوما في طور البحث
for a new blob of dung.
عن قطعة جديدة وصغيرة من الروث.
On the way home, he knows where home is,
في طريق العودة للمنزل، هو يعرف أين يقع المنزل.
and he wants to go straight to it.
ويريد العودة إليه بشكل مستقيم.
The important thing here is that this is not a one-way trip,
الشيء المهم هنا بأن هذه الرحلة ليست باتجاه واحد،
as in most dung beetles. The trip here is repeated
كما هو الحال في أكثر خنافس الروث. هذه الرحلة تتكرر
back and forth between a provisioning site and a nest site.
ذهابا وايابا بين موقع المؤن و موقع العش.
And watch, you're going to see
انظر، سوف ترى
another South African crime taking place right now. (Laughter)
جريمة جنوب افريقية أخرى تحل الآن. (ضحك)
And his neighbor steals one of his dung pellets.
جاره يسرق منه كرات الروث خاصته.
So what we're looking at here
ما يهمنا هنا
is a behavior called path integration.
هو سلوك يطلق عليه اسم دمج المسار.
And what's taking place is that the beetle
وما يحدث هو أن الخنفس
has got a home spot, it goes out on a convoluted path
لديها نقطة منزل، هي تخرج للخارج في مسار ملفوف
looking for food, and then when it finds food,
باحثة عن الطعام، وبعد ذلك عندما تعثر على الطعام،
it heads straight home. It knows exactly where its home is.
تتجه بشكل مستقيم إلى المنزل. هي تعرف بالضبط موق منزلها.
Now there's two ways it could be doing that,
هناك طريقتين تمكنها من القيام بذلك،
and we can test that by displacing the beetle
ونستطيع اختبار ذلك بازاحة الخنفس
to a new position when it's at the foraging site.
إلى مكان آخر عندما يكون في موقع البحث عن الطعام.
If it's using landmarks, it will find its home.
إذا كانت تستخدم نقاط الإستدلال، ستقوم بايجاد منزلها.
If it is using something called path integration,
أما اذا كانت تستخدم مايسمى دمج المسار،
it will not find its home. It will arrive at the wrong spot,
فإنها لن تتمكن من العثور على منزلها. وسوف ينتهي بها المطاف في موقع آخر،
and what it's doing here if it's using path integration
وماتفعله هنا إذا كانت تستخدم دمج المسار
is it's counting its steps or measuring the distance out in this direction.
هو أنها تعد خطواتها أو تقيس المسافة بهذا الاتجاه.
It knows the bearing home, and it knows it should be in that direction.
انها تعرف طريقة المشي إلى المنزل، وتعرف أنه بذلك الإتجاه.
If you displace it, it ends up in the wrong place.
إذا قمت بازاحتها، فسينتهي بها المطاف في المكان الخطأ.
So let's see what happens when we put this beetle
دعونا نرى ماذا سيحصل عندما نضع هذه الخنفسة
to the test with a similar experiment.
قيد الإختبار بتجربة مماثلة.
So here's our cunning experimenter.
هذا هو مجربنا الماكر.
He displaces the beetle,
هو يقوم بازاحة الخنفسة من مكانها الأساسي.
and now we have to see what is going to take place.
والآن دعونا نرى ما سيحصل.
What we've got is a burrow. That's where the forage was.
ما حصلنا عليه هو مخبأ. هذا هو المكان الذي كان فيه مكان البحث عن الطعام.
The forage has been displaced to a new position.
وتم ازاحة مكان البحث عن الطعام إلى مكان آخر.
If he's using landmark orientation,
إذا كان يستخدم التوجيه بواسطة نقاط الإستدلال،
he should be able to find the burrow,
فإنه يجب أن يكون قادرا على ايجاد المخبأ،
because he'll be able to recognize the landmarks around it.
لأنه سيكون قادرا على معرفة نقاط الإستدلال حولها.
If he's using path integration,
إذا كان يستخدم دمج المسار،
then it should end up in the wrong spot over here.
فإنه سينتهي به المطاف في المكان الخطأ هنا.
So let's watch what happens
دعونا نرى ما سيحدث
when we put the beetle through the whole test.
عندما نضع الخنفس عبر الإختبار الكامل.
So there he is there.
إذن هناك هو هناك.
He's about to head home, and look what happens.
كان على وشك التوجه للمنزل، وانظروا ماذا حصل.
Shame.
عار.
It hasn't a clue.
ليس لديه دليل.
It starts to search for its house in the right distance
إنه يبدأ في البحث عن منزله في المسافة الصحيحة
away from the food, but it is clearly completely lost.
بعيدا عن الطعام، لكن من الواضح أنه ضائع تماما.
So we know now that this animal uses path integration
إذن هذا الحيوان يستخدم دمج المسار
to find its way around, and the callous experimenter
لمعرفة طريقه، والمختبر الماكر
leads it top left and leaves it. (Laughter)
وجهها إلى أقصى اليسار وتركها. (ضحك)
So what we're looking at here are a group of animals
ما ننظر إليه هنا هو مجموعة من الحيوانات
that use a compass, and they use the sun as a compass
والتي تستخدم البوصلة، ويستخدمون الشمس كبوصلة
to find their way around,
لإيجاد الطريق من حولهم،
and they have some sort of system
ولديهم نوع من النظام
for measuring that distance,
لقياس هذه المسافة،
and we know that these species here actually
ونحن نعلم أن هذه الفصائل هنا في الحقيقة
count the steps. That's what they use as an odometer,
تعد خطواتها. هذا مايستخدمونه كعداد المسافات،
a step-counting system, to find their way back home.
عداد للخطوات، لايجاد طريق العودة للمنزل.
We don't know yet what dung beetles use.
لا نعلم حتى الآن ما تستخدمه خنافس الروث لفعل ذلك.
So what have we learned from these animals
ماذا تعلمنا من هذه الحيوانات
with a brain that's the size of a grain of rice?
ذات الدماغ بحجم حبة الأرز؟
Well, we know that they can roll balls in a straight line
حسنا، نعرف أنها تستطيع دحرجة الكرات بخط مستقيم
using celestial cues.
باستخدام علامات سماوية.
We know that the dance behavior is an orientation behavior
نعلم أن سلوك الرقص هو سلوك للتوجيه
and it's also a thermoregulation behavior,
وسلوك لتنظيم الحرارة أيضا،
and we also know that they use a path integration system
ونعلم أيضا أنهم يستخدمون نظام دمج المسار
for finding their way home.
لإيجاد طريق العودة للمنزل.
So for a small animal dealing with a fairly revolting substance
من حيوان صغير يتعامل مع مادة مقززة إلى حد ما
we can actually learn an awful lot from these things
نستطيع أن نتعلم كثيرا من الأشياء الرائعة
doing behaviors that you and I couldn't possibly do.
بعمل أنماط من السلوك والتي قد لا نستطيع أنت وأنا فعلها.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)